Tom Hoskins collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Tom Hoskins collection 1963-1999
AFC 2011/026
Hoskins, Tom
58 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in.
31 sound tape reels: analog; 10 in.
4 videocassettes.
1 film reel (16mm): polyester.
approximately 100 photographs: black and white, prints; various sizes.
21 35mm color slides.
approximately 730 items.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of field recordings, studio recordings, and dubs and production masters of performances by blues guitarist Mississippi John Hurt, from the time of Hurt's initial meeting with Tom Hoskins, at Hurt's home in Avalon, Mississippi in March 1963 through various sessions and events from 1963-1965. The collection resulted from Tom Hoskins' relationship with Mississippi John Hurt over the next few years and includes Hoskins' interviews and photographs of John Hurt and his home; includes original letters from John Hurt and Jessie Hurt, with Hoskins' collection of various published articles and ephemera about Mississippi John Hurt, dated 1963-1999. John Hurt and his family moved to Washington, D.C. and he became a popular performer in the blues revival, coffeehouse, and folk music circuits. The collection includes an interview and performances by John Hurt recorded in the Coolidge Auditorium at the Library of Congress, in Washington, D.C. over several days in July, 1963. John Hurt and his family returned to Mississippi in 1966 and Hurt died soon after, on November 2, 1966. A selection from the March 1963 field recordings was issued in 2011 as the album Discovery: The Rebirth of John Hurt, March 3, 1963. Spring Fed Records.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Boggs, Dock, 1898-1971; Hickerson, Joseph C. (Joseph Charles), 1935-; Hoskins, Tom; Hurt, Mississippi John, 1892-1966; Hurt, Mississippi John, 1892-1966--Correspondence.; Mizell, Frank; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Spottswood, Richard K. (Richard Keith)
Subjects
African American musicians--Mississippi--Interviews.; Blues (Music)--1961-1970.; Blues (Music)--Mississippi.
Form/Genre
Blues (Music); Field recordings.; Interviews.; Manuscripts.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Songs.; Sound recordings.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: I. Manuscripts; II. Sound Recordings; III. Graphic Images; IV. Moving Images. The materials are described in the finding aid according to intellectual arrangement rather than numbering sequence (with particular regard to sound recordings).
Acquisition
Suzanne Hoskins Brown, 2011.
Related Material
Mississippi John Hurt recordings collection (AFC 1964/003), Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Publication
Discovery: The Rebirth of John Hurt, March 3, 1963. Spring Fed Records (2011).
Biographical Note
Thomas Bird Hoskins, known as "Tom" in general and as "Fang" to his friends, was a musician and blues music fan who teamed with Dick Spottswood to locate Mississippi John Hurt in March 1963. They had heard Hurt's 1928 recordings and, based on a clue from the song "Avalon blues" ("Avalon's my hometown, always on my mind"), Hoskins went to Mississippi and located Hurt in Avalon, which began the second phase of Hurt's career in music. Hoskins managed Hurt for a time, and stayed in contact with the family after Hurt died. Over the years, legal issues regarding contracts and royalties arose, the last of which was resolved after Hoskins died in 2002, age 60, in Tallahassee, Florida.
Scope and Content
Collection of field recordings, studio recordings, and dubs and production masters of performances by blues guitarist Mississippi John Hurt, from the time of Hurt's initial meeting with Tom Hoskins, at Hurt's home in Avalon, Mississippi in March 1963 through various sessions and events from 1963-1965. The collection resulted from Tom Hoskins' relationship with Mississippi John Hurt over the next few years and includes Hoskins' interviews and photographs of John Hurt and his home; includes original letters from John Hurt and Jessie Hurt, with Hoskins' collection of various published articles and ephemera about Mississippi John Hurt, dated 1963-1999. John Hurt and his family moved to Washington, D.C. and he became a popular performer in the blues revival, coffeehouse, and folk music circuits. The collection includes an interview and performances by John Hurt recorded in the Coolidge Auditorium at the Library of Congress, in Washington, D.C. over several days in July, 1963. John Hurt and his family returned to Mississippi in 1966 and Hurt died soon after, on November 2, 1966. A selection from the March 1963 field recordings was issued in 2011 as the album Discovery: The Rebirth of John Hurt, March 3, 1963. Spring Fed Records.
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Correspondence from Mississippi John Hurt and family, 1963-1972, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Correspondence other individuals, 1965-1999, undated (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Stefan Grossman letter to Tom Hoskins, plus documents sent to him from Rounder, 1976-1992 (Box-folder 1/3)
    The letter to Hoskins is dated October 1, 1992; other documents date from 1976-1980.
  - Permission authorization signed by Jessie Hurt (photocopy), February 16, 1971 (Box-folder 1/4)
    Authorization for the Library of Congress and/or its agents to release to Music Research, Inc., its officers or agents, any and all recordings made by Mississippi John Hurt (her late husband).
  - Business cards, circa 1960s (Box-folder 1/5)
    12 business cards and surrogates for businesses (e.g., McCabe's Guitar Shop), performers (e.g., The Dry City Scat Band), and folklore resources (e.g., Philadelphia Folk Workshop Folklore Center), and others. Some items have contact information for multiple individuals.
  - Concert program, Philadelphia Folk Festival, August 1964 (Box-folder 1/6)
    Two copies and a partial copy of the concert program for Hurt's performance at the 5th annual Philadelphia Folk Festival.
  - Discographies, 1963-1994, undated (Box-folder 1/7)
    Handwritten and photocopied lists of recordings, including photocopied album covers and notes and published reviews, some of works by Hurt, others listed as part of a general blues discography; accompanied by a manila envelope sent from Joe Lee to Bill Tydings of El Frog (with the handwritten note "Hurt discography" on the front). Also includes the booklet from the two-CD set "Mississippi John Hurt: memorial anthology."
  - Music Division, Library of Congress, circa 1960s, 1970 (Box-folder 1/8)
    A two-page list of printed material relating to Hurt, and a one page list of his recordings.
  - Printed lyrics, 1963, undated (Box-folder 1/9)
    Pages from a booklet accompanying vinyl sound recording anthology of the recordings of Charley Patton, a booklet that accompanied the vinyl sound recording "The Mississippi Blues," released as part of the Origin Jazz Library (1963), and a one-page photocopy of the music and lyrics for "Louis Collins."
  - Publicity, circa 1963-1999 (Box-folder 1/10)
    Includes lists of articles about Hurt that could be used for subsequent publicity without charge. Also includes a publicity collage for Skip James. The photo of James has been relocated to Series III.
  - Clippings and articles (originals and photocopies), circa 1960s-2000 (Box-folder 1/11)
    Includes articles and other publications about Hurt, the lawsuit against Hoskins by Hurt's family and other subjects.
  - Master tape logs, circa 1960s (Box-folder 1/12)
    Original folder heading: Master tape logs original and copies Sept. '96. Logs and song lists for some of the recordings in the collection.
  - Logs and song lists (folder 1 of 2), circa 1960s (Box-folder 1/13)
    Handwritten documents.
  - Logs and song lists (folder 2 of 2), circa 1960s (Box-folder 1/14)
    Photocopies of handwritten documents plus typed documents.
  - Manuscript materials from sound recording containers, circa 1960s (Box-folder 1/15)
    Handwritten logs and notes regarding sound recordings.
  - Transcript of Mississippi John Hurt interview (unedited), October 13, 1963 (Box-folder 1/16)
    Typed copy.
  - Transcript of "rediscovery" interview (Box-folder 1/17)
  - List of photographers (Box-folder 1/18)
    Handwritten contact list.
  - Bill Givens: tribute, 1999 (Box-folder 1/19)
    Photocopy of a Billboard article and the eulogy.
  - Articles, liner notes, and other works (originals and photocopies) (Box-folder 2/1)
    Subjects include Hurt and other blues musicians. Contents include an interview transcript (the subject is unidentified, but it is not Hurt).
  - Ephemera, circa 1960s-1990s (Box-folder 2/2)
    Includes liner notes, order forms for recordings, and a copy of the promotional brochure for the 2nd Philadelphia Folk Festival.
  - Stock certificate binder for Music Research, Inc., 1963-1977, undated (Box-folder 2/3)
    One stock certificate, still attached, written out to Mahlon Kline Lea (1977), a receipt for funds received from Hoskins toward the reinstatement of Music Research, Inc.'s corporate charter, stubs for stock certificates sold to Dick Spottswood, Tom Hoskins, Eugene C. Denson, and Mahlon Kline Lea (1963-1966), and legal documents related to Music Research, Inc. (1965-1977, undated).
  - Index cards with song titles (Box-folder 2/4)
    Titles handwritten on 81 3 x 5 in. index cards, some with notes regarding the LP on which the song is found.
  - Address book (without covers) (Box-folder 2/5)
    Handwritten names, addresses, and phone numbers.
  - Address book (with covers) (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Magazines and other publications, 1963-1995 (Box 3)
    Various music-related publications reflecting Hoskins' research interests, including Hurt as well as other blues musicians.
    - Acoustic guitar, March 1998.
    - America illustrated, Summer 1964.
      In Russian and English. Two copies.
    - Blueprint, September 1996.
      Described as "the official news magazine of the British blues connection."
    - Blueprint, October 1996.
    - Blues revue, September/October 1995.
    - Billboard, November 22, 1975.
    - Billboard, September 16, 1995.
    - DC blues calendar, February 1992.
    - Little Sandy review, no. 28 (January-February 1964).
    - Little Sandy review, no. 30 (1965).
    - Memphis flyer, October 21-27, 1999.
    - Sing out, November 1964.
    - Sing out, November 1965.
    - Sing out, February/March 1967.
    - Washington city paper, February 12-18, 1999.
  - Original tape containers, circa 1963-1966; undated (Box 4)
    Tape containers with handwritten notes on them from SR016, SR022, SR033, SR036-SR042, and SR051.
- Series II: Sound Recordings
  Sound recordings were numbered to match the original reel number. The documentation on tape containers indicates that tape 5 is on the same recording as tape 4, and tape 8 is on the same recording as tape 9. Items given the ID numbers SR017 and SR083-SR086 were discovered during the digitization process to be blank--SR017 may never have been used, and SR083-SR086 were bulk-erased. The content may be on other recordings in the collection. Song titles reflect the common use per recording; when Hurt announces a song with a variant of the commonly-used title it is noted. Further variations can be found on accompanying documentation.
  - AFC 2011/026: SR001, April 2, 1963, on 1 side of 1 sound tape reel (15 min., 13 sec.): analog, 15 ips, half track, 1 channel; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr001
    Original ID #1. On tape container: Peter K. Session 2, reel 1.
    - 00:07 Make me a pallet on the floor
      First take.
    - 03:50 Make me a pallet on the floor
      False start.
    - 04:07 Make me a pallet on the floor
      Second take.
    - 06:35 Nobody's dirty business
      Cut off at the end.
    - 07:13 Nobody's dirty business
    - 10:27 Casey Jones
  - AFC 2011/026: SR002, April 2, 1963, on 1 side of 1 sound tape reel (6 min., 22 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 1 channel; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr002
    Original ID #2. Session 2, reel 2. On the tape container: (Pete K) [sic].
    - 00:03 Louis Collins
    - 02:06 Richland woman blues
  - AFC 2011/026: SR003, April 2, 1963, on 1 side of 1 sound tape reel (6 min., 16 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 1 channel; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr003
    Original ID #3. Session 2, reel 3. On the tape container: (Pete K) [sic]. The date March 23, 1963 appears on the tape container with a question mark after it.
    - 00:46 Monday morning blues
  - AFC 2011/026: SR004, April 2, 1963, 1 sound tape reel (10 min., 2 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 1 channel, mono; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr004
    Original ID numbers 4, 5. Session 2, reel 4. On the tape container: (Pete K) [sic].
    - 00:04 Richland woman blues
    - 05:20 Monday Morning blues
  - AFC 2011/026: SR006, July 7, 1963, 1 sound tape reel (17 min., 46 sec.: analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 2 channels; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr006
    Original ID #6. Recorded live at an unidentified club. On the tape container: Pete K.
    - 00:45 Ain't nobody but you
    - 04:57 Keep on knockin'
    - 09:58 Let the mermaid flirt with me
    - 14:37 Rubber dolly
  - AFC 2011/026: SR007, July 7, 1963, 1 sound tape reel (32 min., 39 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 2 channels, stereo; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr007
    Original ID #7.
    - Lazy blues
      Three takes.
    - Blind man sit on the road and cried
    - Blind man sit on the road and cried
      Two takes.
    - Don't you want to go to heaven when the world's on fire
    - Come on home to me Margie
      Incomplete performance.
    - Hey honey, right away
    - Wise and foolish virgins
  - AFC 2011/026: SR009, 1963, July 23-25, 1 sound tape reel (Side A: 12:02; Side B: 13:16): analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 1 channel; 7 in.
    Original ID numbers 8, 9. Session 2, reel 5. On the tape container: (Pete K) [sic].
    - Side A, afc2011026_sr009a
      - Casey Jones
      - My Creole Belle
      - Candy man
      - Louis Collins
    - Side B, afc2011026_sr009b
      - Spike driver blues
      - Waiting for you
      - Frankie and Johnnie
  - AFC 2011/026: SR010, July 23, 1963, on 1 side of 1 sound tape reel (10 min., 24 sec.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1/2 track, 1 channel; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr010
    Original ID #10. Session 2, reel 6. On the tape container: Pete K [Kuykendall].
    - Good morning Miss Carrie
      Instrumental for the most part, with a few words sung.
    - Candy man
      Instrumental.
    - Keep on knockin'
    - Instrumental [unidentified]
  - AFC 2011/026: SR011, July 25, 1963, 1 sound tape reel (14 min., 23 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 2 channels; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr011
    Original ID #11. On the tape container: (Master.....not really master) Reel I / Reel 7.
    - Salty dog
    - Walking the floor over you
    - Poor boy, long ways from home
    - Good morning Miss Carrie
  - AFC 2011/026: SR012, July 7, 1963, 1 sound tape reel (14 min., 31 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 1 channel; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr012
    Original ID #12. "9."
    - If you don't want me
    - Instrumental [unidentified]
      Fragment of a song.
    - If you don't want me
    - Pera Lee
      Hurt uses a slide with his guitar on this song.
    - Four o'clock blues
  - AFC 2011/026: SR013, March 1964, 1 sound tape reel (18 min., 50 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 1 channel; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr013
    Original ID #13. MJH 51 dub master L 1609-1. L 1609 may be the matrix number for the commercial sound recording (LP) by Hurt, called "Worried blues." The recording seems to have been made in front of a live audience.
    - Lazy blues
    - Farther along
    - Sliding Delta
      Spoken introduction and song.
    - Nobody cares for me blues
    - Cow hookin' blues
  - AFC 2011/026: SR014, March 1964, 1 sound tape reel (19 min., 36 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1/2 track, 2 channels; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr014
    Original ID #14. MJH 52 dub master L 1610-1. See note for SR013.
    - Taking Casey Jones
    - The great judgment morning
    - Worried blues
    - Oh Mary, don't you weep
    - Baby, please come home
  - AFC 2011/026: SR015, March 3, 1963, 1 sound tape reel (Side B: 1 hr., 5 min., 45 sec.; Side A: 1 hr., 4 min., 25 sec.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1/2 track, 1 channel; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr015
    Discovery reel #1. Voices can be heard in the background, and in conversation with Hurt, during and between songs. Recorded in Avalon, Mississippi by Tom Hoskins. A rooster can be heard in the background on the untitled tune and during the subsequent tuning and conversation. Gertrude Conley (Hurt's first wife) and Jenny McCrain both sing without accompaniment. Jessie Hurt was John Hurt's second wife.
    - Side B, afc2011026_sr015
      - Cow hookin' blues
        Instrumental version.
      - John talks about his life and history
        Others listening join the conversation at times.
      - Nobody's dirty business
      - Casey Jones
      - Stagolee
      - John talks about history of the song and the person Stagolee
      - Richland woman blues
      - Coffee blues
      - Do Lord, remember me
        Includes two false starts and a complete version.
      - Take my hand
      - Candy man
      - Waiting for you
      - Got the blues (can't be satisfied)
      - Frankie and Albert
        Cut off at the end; distortion develops about the same time.
    - Side A, afc2011026_sr015
      - Casey Jones
      - Waiting for you
        Duet with Jessie.
      - [conversation]
      - Got the blues (can't be satisfied)
      - Let the mermaid flirt with me
        Hurt announces the song as Mermaid blues.
      - You are my sunshine
        Instrumental fragment of the song.
      - Ain't nobody but you
      - Make me a pallet on the floor
      - Spike driver blues
        Fragment of the song.
      - Praying on the old camp ground
      - Since I've laid my burden down
      - Louis Collins
      - Interview
      - Richland woman blues
      - Blues all day long
      - Through the years I keep on toiling
        Sung by Gertrude Conley (Hurt's first wife).
      - Precious Lord take my hand
        Sung by Jenny McCrain (Gertrude Conley's sister).
  - AFC 2011/026: SR016, March 3, 1963; July 7, 1965, on 1 side of 1 sound tape reel (1 hr., 3 min., 5 sec.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1/2 track, 1 channel; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr016
    Original ID #16. John Hurt biography #1. On the tape container: "This is the first (post discovery) John Hurt Recording" (G.R.). "same as 15." Recorded in Avalon, Mississippi by Tom Hoskins on March 3, 1963. Conversations and background noise can be heard throughout the recording. While the documentation notes "re-recorded: Adelphi Studios" on July 7, 1965, this is the recording of March 3, 1963. SR015b is a slightly different version of this recording, with the addition of "Frankie and Johnnie" and the exclusion of "Through the years I keep on toiling" and "Precious Lord take my hand."
    - Frankie and Johnnie
      The tape cuts off during the performance.
    - Casey Jones
    - Waiting for you
    - [conversation]
    - Got the blues (Can't be satisfied)
    - Let the mermaid flirt with me
    - You are my sunshine
    - Ain't nobody but you
    - Make me a pallet on the floor
    - Spike driver blues
    - Praying on the old camp ground
    - Since I've laid my burden down
    - Louis Collins
    - Interview
    - Richland woman blues
    - Blues all day long
  - AFC 2011/026: SR018, April 2, 1964, 1 sound tape reel (30 min., 9 sec.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1/2 track, 2 channels, mono; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr018
    Original ID #18. Voice of America program. The name "Peter Kendall" appears on the tape box, but may be a mistake, and could be Peter Kuykendall.
    - Introduction by Peter Kendall (interviewer)
    - My Creole belle
      The introduction is spoken over the song.
    - [Interview - background, early career in music, story of rediscovery by Hoskins, and other topics]
    - Avalon blues
    - [Interview, continued]
    - Louis Collins
    - [Interview - Casey Jones story]
    - Casey Jones
    - Richland woman blues
    - [Interview, continued]
    - Good morning Miss Carrie
    - [Conclusion]
      Peter Kendall signs off, speaking over last part of the song.
  - AFC 2011/026: SR019, 1 sound tape reel (29 min., 39 sec.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1/2 track, 2 channels, mono; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr019
    Original ID #19. Studio One: Mississippi John Hurt. Intended for broadcast on Voice of America. The announcer asks questions in English, and translates into French for the intended audience. The interview takes place between the songs, and also serves to introduce songs.
    - [Introduction]
      Spoken in French by an unidentified announcer
    - Lonesome is I
    - See See Rider
    - Nobody's Business
    - Trouble I've had it all my days
    - Do Lord, remember me
    - Stewball
      The song cuts off at very end, following a brief fade-out.
  - AFC 2011/026: SR020, October 30, 1964, 1 sound tape reel (Side A: 8 min., 35 sec.; Side B: 26 min., 52 sec.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1/2 track, 2 channels; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr020
    Original ID #20. Mississippi John Hurt recorded at The Unicorn Coffee House, 825 Boylston St, Boston, Massachusetts. Reel # 1. John introduces each song. Because the tape ends in mono, the engineer created two digital files (identified as A and B files). This is an edited copy of the original (applause between songs has been cut; although other material may have been edited out).
    - Side A
      - What a friend we have in Jesus
      - Candy man
    - Side B
      - Blessed be the name
      - Worried blues
      - Avalon blues
      - Sliding Delta
      - Spike driver blues
      - Chicken
      - Candy man
  - AFC 2011/026: SR021, November 1, 1964, on one side of 1 sound tape reel (29 min., 42 sec.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1/2 track, stereo; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr021
    Original ID #21. John Hurt and Skip James, Nov. 1, 1964. Recorded at The Unicorn Coffee House, 825 Boylston Street, Boston, Massachusetts. Reel # 2.
    - Farther along
    - Lonesome valley
    - Louis Collins
    - Lonesome is I
    - Worried blues
    - Monday morning blues
    - Chicken
    - Stocktime (Buck dance)
  - AFC 2011/026: SR022, October 26, 1964, on one side of 1 sound tape reel (30 min., 15 sec.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1/2 track, mono; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr022
    Original ID #22. #3. Studio session, Cambridge, MA. The voices of two unidentified men can be heard in the background, in conversation with John.
    - Candy man
    - Joe Turner blues
    - My Creole belle
    - Louis Collins
    - Cow hookin' blues
    - Candy man
    - Rubber dolly
  - AFC 2011/026: SR023, on one side of 1 sound tape reel (18 min., 42 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1⁄2 track, 2 channels; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr023
    Original ID #23. On tape container: MJH by? at? Denson Boston Dub? Recorded in front of a live audience. "Denson" may be Ed Denson who, along with John Fahey, rediscovered Bukka White, another blues singer.
    - I been cryin' since you been gone
      Hurt stops playing the song suddenly, then is prompted to go on to play "Funky butt."
    - Funky butt
    - Lazy blues
    - Long lonesome blues
    - Frankie and Johnnie
  - AFC 2011/026: SR024, March 24, 26, 29, 1963; April 2, 1963, on one side of on 1 side of 1 sound tape reel (11 min., 10 sec.): analog, 15 ips, 1⁄2 track, 1 channel; 7 in.; afc2011026_sr024